Guide to the Norman Thomas Papers TAM.423
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Norman Thomas Papers
1925-1969
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968
Bell, Daniel, 1919-2011
TAM.423
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Norman Mattoon Thomas (1884–1968), was a leading American socialist, pacifist, author, and six-time presidential candidate for president on the ticket of the Socialist Party of America, between 1928 and 1948. The collection contains correspondence, including some in his capacity as co-executive director of the League for Industrial Democracy, unpublished political and biographical writings, biographical sketches of his grandfather, Stephen Mattoon, Daniel Bell's 1954 correspondence with socialist luminaries around the world in preparation for the celebration of Thomas's seventieth birthday, and one typescript each by Broadus Mitchell and Emil Rieve, president of the American Federation of Hosiery Workers.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
A portion of the materials was donated by Daniel Bell, date unknown; the provenance of the remainder is unknown. The accession number associated with this collecion is 1950.238.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
I, Papers, 1925-1969.
Historical/Biographical Note
Norman Mattoon Thomas (1884–1968), was a leading American socialist, pacifist, author, and six-time presidential candidate on the Socialist Party of America ticket, between 1928 and 1948. Born in Marion, Ohio, he was a graduate of Princeton University, attended Union Theological Seminary, where he became a socialist, and was ordained as a Presbyterian minister in 1911. Thomas opposed the United States' entry into the First World War, a position that earned him the disapproval of many in his socialist circle and in his church. He founded a magazine, The World Tomorrow, in 1918. In 1921-22 he was associate editor of The Nation, and, also in 1922, he became co-director of the League for Industrial Democracy. He was later one of the founders of the National Civil Liberties Bureau (the precursor of the American Civil Liberties Union) and of the Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy. At first Thomas was outspoken in opposing the U.S. involvement in the Second World War, and he served on the board of the America First Committee. However, once the United States was attacked by the Japanese, he supported U.S. war effort, while opposing the war-time internment of Japanese Americans. Thomas frequently spoke on the difference between democratic socialism and Communism; his early admiration for the Russian Revolution and later sympathy with Popular Front activity evolved into fervent anti-Communism. He wrote several books, among them his defense of World War I conscientious objectors, Is Conscience a Crime? (1927) and Socialism Re-examined (1963).
Sources:
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Thomas (August 22, 2008)
Scope and Content Note
This small collection contains some of Norman Thomas' correspondence, including some in his capacity as co-executive director of the League for Industrial Democracy, unpublished political and biographical writings, including "Forty Years of Communism," a 1939 radio speech on the revision of the Neutrality Act, a statement to the membership of the New York City Socialist Party, circa 1936, an undated memorandum on Local 306, Motion Picture Operators, biographical sketches of his grandfather, Stephen Mattoon (provided by the Johnson C. Smith University Library, North Carolina), Daniel Bell's 1954 correspondence with socialist luminaries around the world in preparation for the celebration of Thomas' seventieth birthday, and one typescript each by Broadus Mitchell and Emil Rieve, President of the American Federation of Hosiery Workers.
Speeches.; Socialists -- United States.; Socialism -- United States.; Autobiographies.; Correspondence.; Pacifists |z United States.; Manuscripts for publication.; League for Industrial Democracy; Bell, Daniel, 1919-2011; Mattoon, Stephen.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Moving Picture Machine Operators of the United States and Canada. Local 306 (New York, N.Y.); Mitchell, Broadus, 1892-1988; Rieve, Emil, 1892-1975.; Socialist Party (U.S.); Bell, Daniel, 1919-2011
- Series I: Papers, 1925-1969, 134198
  - Bell, Daniel: Correspondence, Nov 1947; 134216 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, General, 1946-1964; 134215 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Forty Years of Communism" (typescript, 18 pp.), 1958; 134214 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "From a Book Without a Name: For My Family, Not for Publication" (typescript, 21 pp.), circa 1947; 134213 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "From Unpublished Reminiscences of Norman Thomas" (typescript, 3 pp.), Aug 24, 1947; 134212 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - League for Industrial Democracy: Correspondence, 1925-1931; 134211 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mattoon, Stephen [grandfather of NT]: Biographical Sketches Provided by Johnson C. Smith University Library (North Carolina), undated; 134210 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memorandum on Local # 306, Motion Picture Operators, undated; 134209 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mitchell, Broadus: "Sabotage upon Civilization", circa 1935; 134208 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Norman Thomas in Final Appeal" (Socialist National Campaign Committee), Nov 6, 1928; 134207 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Printed Ephemera: Card Announcing a Debate between Norman Thomas and Paul Douglas on the Topic "Should America Follow the Policy of Collective Security?", Feb 24, 1938; 134206 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Peace on Earth, Good Will to Men", circa 1939; 134204 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photograph, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 050, Folder 11)
  - Radio Speech on Revision of Neutrality Act, Oct 13, 1939; 134205 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rieve, Emil (president, American Federation of Hosiery Workers): "Planned Consumption and Production", circa 1934; 134203 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Security versus Abundance", circa 1935; 134202 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 70th Birthday Celebration: Daniel Bell Correspondence, Oct 5, 1954-Dec 20, 1954, undated; 134201 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Thomas Supports the War", Dec 1, 1941; 134200 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "To the Membership of New York City [Socialist Party]": Statement by Norman Thomas, circa 1936; 134199 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter to Richard Reiss, Americans for Reappraisal of Far Eastern Policy, re "Vietnam Talk", 1965-10-20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Vietnam Talk, 1965 (Box Shared Tamiment 013)